בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is דף נא, daf nun-aleph,
51, and we are wrapping up the sort of meta discussion of
what type of דרשות drashot are legitimate sort of doubly derived דרשות,
drashot, specifically in the area of קדשים kodshim in which you have
more restrictions about when you can apply certain דרשות drashot as I
just have repeated few times now. Two rules that don't apply in
other areas of הלכה: halakha: one is is that when the תורה
Torah speaks about a requirement, normally you assume it's a requirement, ולקחתם
לכם פרי עץ הדר. u-lekachtem lachem pri etz hadar. Okay, there's no
discussion like, "oh, does it really have to be a פרי? pri?
Does it really have to be an עץ? etz? Does it really
have to be הדר?" hadar? But by the קרבנות korbanot there's so
many requirements that the assumption is is that unless it's repeated, it's
not מעכב, meakev, it doesn't prevent the קרבן korban from being valid.
That's point number one. And point number two is is that this
idea that if you learn A to B, can you go from
B to C? In other areas the answer is yes, but in
קרבנות korbanot there's a limit when you can say that. Again, probably
also because there are just so many details that if you were
to do that you would get overwhelmed with the amount of הלכות.
halakhot. So the גמרא Gemara went through four different ways that you
can connect A to B: one is a היקש, hekesh, the other
is גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah, קל וחומר, kal va-chomer, and בנין אב.
binyan av. And then it did a chart of 4 by 4
to say can you go from היקש hekesh to היקש? hekesh? The
answer was no. Can you do היקש hekesh to גזירה שוה? gezeirah
shavah? The answer was no. See, now you're going to see if
I remember it. Can you do היקש hekesh to קל וחומר? kal
va-chomer? The answer was yes. Can you do היקש hekesh to בנין
אב? binyan av? I think we didn't answer that one, I don't
remember. Anyway. Okay, so
anyway, went through all those possibilities. And the last so we're left
with one little last piece of that now, which is the בנין
אב binyan av row of that of that of that chart. So
that's what we pick up here on נא. nun-aleph. And it says
the following,
five lines down on נא עמוד א: nun-aleph amud-aleph: דבר הלמד בבנין
אב מהו שיהא למד בהיקש ובגזירה שוה ובבנין אב. Davar ha-lamed be-binyan
av,
mah she-hu lamed be-hekesh u-ve-gezeirah
shavah u-ve-binyan av.
So thankfully because it's asking all of them together, it's going to
deal with it in a pretty summary fashion. Okay, things that are
בנין אב, binyan av, can you do all the other things? Can
you בנין אב binyan av and then from בנין אב binyan av
to היקש, hekesh, בנין אב binyan av to גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah,
בנין אב binyan av to קל וחומר, kal va-chomer, בנין אב binyan
av to בנין אב? binyan av? Are you allowed to do those
things? Again, when you're within the world of קדשים? kodshim? And again,
part of the question also is how do you determine if you're
in the world of קדשים? kodshim? Does it go by the source?
Does it go by the application? If you have three things, A,
B, and C, which one of them have to be in קדשים
kodshim in order to assume that the restrictive rules would apply? Anyway,
what's the story when you start with a בנין אב? binyan av?
When you start with something that's like a paradigm and then you
want to continue it on. So the גמרא Gemara says: פשט מהא
חדא. Pashat mi-achada.
We can at least conclude one of these. בפני מה אמרו לן
בדם כשר. Bifnei mah amru lan ba-dam kasher.
So the הלכה halakha is if you put things on the מזבח
mizbeiach that are פסול, pasul, you're allowed to leave them on the
מזבח mizbeiach with a couple of exceptions. And there's a debate which
are the exceptions, which are the things that even if they're on
the מזבח mizbeiach they have to come off. This is going according
to the position of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says that he
has a larger category of things that if they're on the מזבח
mizbeiach have to come off. And what he says which would have
to come off are things which were שחט shechted at night or
the blood was spilled or the blood went out of the בית
המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, etc. So those are things that if they're on
the מזבח mizbeiach have to come down. So then why do other
things, why are they allowed to stay on, is the question. Where
do you draw the line? Okay, and the line we're going to
determine it based on like a type of a בנין אב binyan
av that certain things are allowed to stay on the מזבח mizbeiach
if they're put on. So מפני מה אמרו, mifnei mah amru, why
did they say לן בדם כשר, lan ba-dam kasher, that if the
blood slept overnight and was only put on the מזבח mizbeiach after
it was already a day later, you're allowed to keep stuff on
the מזבח, mizbeiach, why is that? שהרי לן באימורין כשר. She-harei lan
be-imurin kasher. Because we know that if the אימורין imurin were slept
overnight and are נותר notar and are put on the מזבח, mizbeiach,
they're כשר. kasher. How do we know that? לן באימורין כשר, Lan
be-imurin kasher, now how do you know that? Because שהרי לן בבשר
כשר. she-harei lan be-basar kasher. Because we know at least by the
case of a שלמים, shelamim, you're allowed to eat the meat for
two days. So of course part of the problem here is how
can you make an inference from something that's fundamentally kosher? But okay,
the גמרא Gemara will get to that, but we'll worry about that
in a minute. But since there are times where the meat is
kosher even if it's a day late, so therefore the אימורין imurin
if they slept overnight are כשר. kasher. Okay, and that's it's meat
and it's meat, it's more similar, it's also stuff that is put
on the fire to burn, at least some meat is put on
the fire to burn by an עולה, olah, so you can apply
that also to the אימורין. imurin. Also it's not the thing that
makes the קרבן korban valid, that makes the קרבן korban כשר. kasher.
So that's a more obvious comparison, comparing the אימורין imurin to comparing
the meat. Again, although there are differences, the meat in the case
of a שלמים shelamim is eaten, the meat in the case of
a שלמים shelamim is allowed to be eaten the second day. But
anyway, we start by comparing the meat to the אימורין. imurin. If
the meat sometimes a day late is כשר, kasher, the אימורין imurin
a day late can be left on the altar. And now if
that's true about the אימורין, imurin, it's... about other things that are
put on the altar, it's true about the blood. So that's a
בנין אב binyan av based on a בנין אב. binyan av. Okay,
so that's an answer at least to that question. Let's just finish
this up, okay? So the ברייתא braita continues.
Okay. יוצא, yotze, now how do you know if stuff was taken
out of the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and put on the altar
that it can remain there? הואיל ויוצא כשר בבמה, ho'il v'yotze kasher
b'bamah, because by a במה bamah the stuff is outside of the
מקדש Mikdash and it's legitimate. So therefore stuff that's put out of
the מקדש Mikdash can be left on the altar again. It's similar
to the שלמים shelamim point. By, it's even worse in, well I
don't know if it's worse, but anyway by a במה bamah there's
not even a concept of יוצא, yotze, that is the right place.
It's not in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, but anywhere it is
is the right place. So anyway, and you're also going from a
case that's fundamentally כשר kasher to apply it to a case that's
fundamentally פסול, pasul, but בדיעבד bedi'avad if it's on the altar, it's
allowed to remain. So these are not the world's greatest comparisons. טמא,
tamei, now how do you know if something is טמא, tamei, a
meat is טמא tamei and it's put on the altar, how do
you know that that is
כשר? kasher? הואיל והותר בעבודת ציבור, ho'il v'hutar b'avodat tzibur, because there's
times when טמא tamei is permissible if it's טומאה הותרה בציבור. tumah
hutrah b'tzibur. Again, not a great comparison because טומאה הותרה בציבור tumah
hutrah b'tzibur is when the people are טמא, tamei, not when the
meat is טמא. tamei. Okay, I mean other, maybe maybe you could
have spoken about ריצוי ציץ, ritzuy tzitz, but then that's not a
comparison, that's a fundamental הלכה. halacha. I mean that's directly saying if
ריצוי ציץ ritzuy tzitz allows it to remain on.
But what does that mean? Like, it's so obvious, everybody, so what
kind of, what's the הוה אמינא hava amina of all these?
Well let's take a look. חוץ לזמנו, chutz lizmano, now how do
you know חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano if it's left on the altar
is כשר? kasher? הואיל ומרצה לפיגולו. ho'il u'mratze l'pigulo. חוץ לזמנו chutz
lizmano means that not לן, lan, that things waited over that it
would be a case of לן. lan.
But you had an intent
something basically פיגול pigul meat that was then put on the מזבח.
mizbe'ach. So the answer is it's כשר kasher because since when you
have פיגול pigul thoughts, it's still considered like the rest of the
קרבן korban was done correctly in order to make the קרבן פיגול,
korban pigul, so your פיגול pigul thoughts make it seem like well
within the context of פיגול, pigul, פיגול pigul thoughts don't invalidate. So
that's considered like the rest of the קרבן korban was done correctly,
which is what you need to make פיגול. pigul. So since within
that פיגול pigul context, פיגול pigul thoughts are not seen as a
separate invalidity, it's considered still to work within the idea of מרצה,
mratze, making the קרבן korban valid. So here too, that's good enough
to let it stay on the altar. חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo הואיל
והוקש לחוץ לזמנו. ho'il v'hukash l'chutz lizmano. And חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo
thought is connected to a חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano thought.
שקיבלו פסולין וזרקו דמן. shekiblu psulin v'zarku daman. So how do you
know if פסול pasul people, כהנים, kohanim, caught the blood and threw
it, that you're allowed to let the meat remain on the altar?
Where is the analogy there to something that otherwise would be kosher?
So it says בהנך פסולים דחזו לעבודת ציבור. b'hanach psulim d'chazu l'avodat
tzibur. We're talking about the type of פסולים psulim that are כשר
kasher for a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur, which really limits you to
one, meaning if the כהנים kohanim are טמא. tamei. Okay, so the
reason we know these things are כשר kasher is because in some
other scenarios, you know, loosely associated scenarios, a similar type of a
thing would be כשר. kasher. So we know that even though it
is פסול, pasul, if it's on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, it's allowed to
remain on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So now the גמרא Gemara says the
following question. Anyway, all of that is a proof that you can
do a בנין אב binyan av based on a בנין אב. binyan
av. But now the גמרא Gemara essentially asks Michael's question, or the
question we've been pointing out all along: וכי דנים דבר שלא בהכשירו
מדבר שבהכשירו? v'chi danim davar shelo b'hechsheiro midavar sheb'hechsheiro? How can you
apply something that fundamentally is כשר, kasher, like meat on the second
day by a שלמים, shelamim, or stuff that's outside the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash by a במה, bamah, and use that to say, ah,
from this we see that when it's done in a way that
makes it פסול pasul and you put it on the מזבח, mizbe'ach,
it's allowed to remain on the מזבח? mizbe'ach? It's completely not relevant
that something that is fundamentally כשר. kasher. So the גמרא Gemara says,
תניא מזאת תורת העולה ריבה סמוך לו. tanya mizot torat ha'olah ribah
samuch lo. You're right. In principle, we really know
that things can remain on the altar even though they're fundamentally פסול
pasul from זאת תורת העולה. zot torat ha'olah. תורה אחת לכל העולים.
torah achat l'chol ha'olim. Anything that goes on the altar is allowed
to remain on the altar. So it's really not like we started
saying like, well, I'll start by assuming that stuff has to come
down. Oh, sometimes meat on a second day is כשר, kasher, it's
fine, I'll let meat stay on the altar. No, we don't start
by, if we started by assuming that it had to come down,
none of these comparisons would have worked, and it would not have
argued for me that the stuff is allowed to stay on the
altar. So that, you're right, they're all bad. It doesn't, this is
not a strong enough comparison to make the point that it can
stay on the altar. These things are fundamentally כשר kasher in other
contexts. The point is is that we fundamentally start with the idea
that everything פסול pasul that goes on the altar is allowed to
remain there. Then we have to identify a few things that are
so bad that they wouldn't even be included in this rule. So
therefore these comparisons are very weak comparisons, but what these comparisons are
arguing for is that they're not the worst type of problem and
therefore these things are still fundamentally in the category of זאת תורת
העולה. zot torat ha'olah. And how do I know they're not the
worst problems? Because in some weakly associated case, you could imagine something
being כשר kasher like this in a weakly... In a weakly associated
case. So that just as a way of showing that they're still
within the fundamental category of זאת תורת העולה. Zos Toras ha-Olah. Okay,
so this is not the basis to argue that it stays on
the altar. Everything stays on the altar. זאת תורת העולה. Zos Toras
ha-Olah. We just know that there's some few things that go off.
Which are the few things that go off? Well, all of these
are still probably in the stay-on category because there's still enough of
some comparison to other things like them that are כשר. kosher. Okay,
so that's really the point.
The point is not that these are our strong argument to say
they stay on. Now, the ברייתא braita actually says once you say
that you might have lost your proof of a בנין אב binyan
av based on a בנין אב. binyan av. Because since we're really
not learning from here that it stays on, we're just learning from
here don't put these in the take-off category because, you know, they're
not the worst. So once that's true, you can't really prove that
we can learn a הלכה halacha from a בנין אב binyan av
based on a בנין אב, binyan av, because here the real הלכה
halacha is learned from זאת תורת העולה. Zos Toras ha-Olah. Okay, so
it could be that in the end the גמרא Gemara actually hasn't
concluded any of the questions about starting with a בנין אב binyan
av or where can you go from there. Thankfully we are now
done with all that meta, okay. What is the type of double-derived
הלכה halacha that you can apply by קדשים? kodshim? And now we
get back, although we're not out of the world of דרשות drashos
because still, we're in דרשות, drashos, but at least we're in the
direct דרשות, drashos, not in the meta-discussion. Okay, and now we're going
to go to the next הלכה halacha of the משנה mishnah about
the חטאות. chata'os. So the next הלכה halacha of the חטאות chata'os
says, שירי הדם, shirei hadam, the remnant of the blood, you would
spill
on the western base of the outer מזבח. mizbe'ach. Okay, so here
you have the inner חטאת. chatas.
Okay, here you got your מזבח. mizbe'ach. You've got your חטאת, chatas,
okay, it's on the צפון tzafon of the מזבח. mizbe'ach. That's the
צפון tzafon of the מזבח. mizbe'ach. You cast the blood at the
צפון. tzafon. If it's an inner חטאת, chatas, you bring the blood
here and you put them on, you know, the פרוכת paroches or
the מזבח. mizbe'ach. And then the remainder of the blood you spill
on the base here of the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Okay, so, and it's
the specific specifically it says the west base. So you spill it
over there. So the question is, where do we know that from?
Okay, why חטאת? chatas? So שירי הדם
מאי טעמא? shirei hadam mai ta'ama? Where do you know this from?
Or like מנא הני מילי. mena hani mili. אמר קרא, Amar kra,
אל יסוד
מזבח העולה אשר פתח אהל מועד.
el yesod mizbe'ach ha-olah asher
pesach ohel moed.
It says that you now pour it at the base of the
מזבח העולה mizbe'ach ha-olah which is by the opening of אהל מועד.
Ohel Moed. So means as soon the one facing the opening of
אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, that is the that's the south one? That's
where you spill it. Okay, oh the south, excuse me, the west
one, that is where you spill it. Now, the מאי טעמא mai
ta'ama as I said, it's funny, it could have said מנא הני
מילי. mena hani mili. There was a גרסא girsa in this גמרא
Gemara מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, and the answer was ההוא דפגע ברישא,
hahu depaga bereisha, which is more of a reason than a פסוק,
pasuk, which is as you're going out, the first part of the
base that you hit is the one on the west. So that's
why there's a long תוספות Tosafos discussing is that the reason, or
is and then it's an interesting principle of is this a principle
of sort of like אין מעבירין על המצוות. ein ma'avirin al ha-mitzvot.
When you encounter a מצוה mitzvah you don't bypass it to do
another one. So is that what it's based on or is it
based on a פסוק? pasuk? In the end he goes with right
so what is the פסוק pasuk based on otherwise the philosophy...
Well, it could do that, but anyway, but תוספות Tosafos more wants
to say is it are we reading it as a גזירת הכתוב
gzeiras hakasuv or are we reading it as a just a reason
of אין מעבירין? ein ma'avirin? In the end, for various reasons, תוספות
Tosafos sides goes with the way our גמרא Gemara reads, which is
really based on the way רש"י Rashi has edited our גמרא Gemara
to just base it straight on a פסוק pasuk and not say
that it's based on some concept of ההוא דפגע ברישא. hahu depaga
bereisha. No there are various technical reasons why תוספות Tosafos says that,
but anyway, that's two ways of conceptualizing it. Part of the interesting
question is where do you spill the blood by the outer חטאת?
chatas? And there there's a מחלוקת, machlokes, because by the outer חטאות
chata'os you go up here, you do it here, here, here, here
and you come down here. So where are the two possibilities? If
it's based on that it's just גזירת הכתוב, gzeiras hakasuv, an explicit
פסוק פתח אהל מועד, pasuk pesach ohel moed, you would move over
you would go over here and you would do it in the
in the west. But if it's based on the idea of ההוא
דפגע ברישא, hahu depaga bereisha, as you're going down here, you would
do it here in the south. So that's actually a מחלוקת machlokes
where you do the outer חטאות. chata'os. Okay, so whether so that
might be based exactly on this. Is it based on the concept
of ההוא דפגע ברישא hahu depaga bereisha or is it based on
just the פסוק פתח אהל מועד? pasuk pesach ohel moed? All right.
תוספות Tosafos by the way says well why wouldn't it be based
on this idea of ההוא דפגע ברישא hahu depaga bereisha of אין
מעבירין על המצוות? ein ma'avirin al ha-mitzvos? תוספות Tosafos says אין מעבירין
על המצוות ein ma'avirin al ha-mitzvos is don't abandon this מצוה mitzvah
for another מצוה. mitzvah. Here I'm doing the מצוה mitzvah of spilling
the blood. The question of which is the right place on the
base to do the מצוה mitzvah is not necessarily answered by the
principle of אין מעבירין על המצוות. ein ma'avirin al ha-mitzvot. Okay, anyway,
so but that's what we say. You do it here at the
west base. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this, not to be
confused with the West Bank. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. ההוא דפגע ברישא. hahu depaga bereisha. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan.
אל יסוד מזבח העולה. el yesod mizbeach ha-olah. Now
רש"י Rashi
points out, excuse me, there are three פסוקים pesukim in ויקרא Vayikra
where it speaks about spilling the blood by the base of the
מזבח, mizbeach,
and five פסוקים, pesukim, excuse me, that speak about spilling it.
But three of them, it says explicitly מזבח העולה. mizbeach ha-olah. So
what are the three? So the three are, it says, let me
just check רש"י Rashi here.
If
you
look at רש"י Rashi five lines down in the medium-sized lines, רש"י
Rashi says the following: חמש
פרשיות הן בחטאת, chamesh parshiyos hen b'chatas,
של פר משיח shel par mashiach ושל העלם דבר v'shel helam davar
ושל העלם דבר v'shel helam davar you know, העלם דבר. helam davar.
So there's the two inner חטאות chata'os that it mentions at the
end of פרשת ויקרא, parshas Vayikra, not ספר ויקרא. sefer Vayikra.
שהן פנימיות, she-hen p'nimiyos, and those are inner חטאות. chata'os. Those are
the communal ones or whatever, פר משיח par mashiach and פר העלם
דבר. par helam davar. ושל שעיר נשיא, v'shel se'ir nasi, and then
the שעיר se'ir of the נשיא. nasi. And then הכבשת יחיד v'ha-kivsas
yachid and the שעירה, se'irah, okay. And the two inner ones and
the שעיר נשיא se'ir nasi it says, it says, בשפיכת שיריהם אל
יסוד מזבח העולה. bishfichas shireihem el yesod mizbeach ha-olah. And the two
outer ones, ושהן חיצוניות, v'she-hen chitzoniyos, it says אל יסוד המזבח, el
yesod hamizbeach, okay. So you've got,
you
have...
Yes, well that's obvious then it would be מזבח העולה. mizbeach ha-olah.
If it's outside it stays outside. The חידוש chiddush is that the
inside stuff is spilled outside. What? I mean you needed to say
that by the way that are brought inside.
We're gonna get to that. All my good markers disappeared. I don't
know what happened. Okay, you have the חטאת chatas of the פר
כהן משיח. par kohen mashiach.
Now you have העלם דבר של ציבור. helam davar shel tzibbur.
Okay, those are inner,
those are פנימי. p'nimi. And then you have
שעיר נשיא, se'ir nasi, excuse me.
And then you have כבשה של יחיד kivsah shel yachid
and the שעירה של יחיד. se'irah shel yachid. Okay, and those are
the five, that's the end of פרשת ויקרא. parshas Vayikra. Go open
up your פרשת ויקרא, parshas Vayikra, that's the end. And in these
three it says
אל
יסוד מזבח העולה.
el yesod mizbeach
ha-olah. And these two it just says spill it אל יסוד המזבח.
el yesod hamizbeach. Okay, so we're gonna focus on why it says
העולה ha-olah in those three. Okay, we're not really gonna go to
these two. Why does it say מזבח העולה mizbeach ha-olah in those
three? So let's take a look. Okay, so here's a ברייתא. baraisa.
תנו רבנן. tano rabbanan.
אל יסוד מזבח העולה el yesod mizbeach ha-olah ולא יסוד מזבח הפנימי.
v'lo yesod mizbeach hapnimi. Okay, so spill the blood even though it's
an inner חטאת, chatas, don't spill it at the base of the
inner מזבח, mizbeach, spill it at the base of the outer מזבח.
mizbeach. So that's pretty clear why it had to say העולה, ha-olah,
which is what I think Michael you were just saying. If you're
in the inner מזבח, mizbeach, you want to make it clear don't
spill it there. Go to the outer מזבח mizbeach and spill it
there. אל יסוד מזבח העולה אין לו יסוד לפנימי עצמו. el yesod
mizbeach ha-olah ein lo yesod l'p'nimi atzmo. So, oh by the way,
the reason you're not spilling it at the base of the פנימי
p'nimi is that יסוד מזבח העולה yesod mizbeach ha-olah is telling you
only the מזבח העולה mizbeach ha-olah has a יסוד. yesod. The inner
מזבח mizbeach don't even make a יסוד yesod to it. It don't
have a base to it. It's just one basic straight, you know,
what's it called, perpendicular solid. Well you need to say מזבח העולה
mizbeach ha-olah then. Well from this פסוק, pasuk, this is the פסוק
pasuk from which you learn that the inner מזבח mizbeach does not
have it. Okay, rectangular solid I mean to say. Anyway,
okay. So, אל יסוד מזבח העולה. el yesod mizbeach ha-olah. Last one,
אל יסוד מזבח העולה תן יסוד למזבח של עולה. el yesod mizbeach
ha-olah ten yesod l'mizbeach shel olah. Give the base to the מזבח
של עולה. mizbeach shel olah. Now what does that mean? So if
you take a quick peek, turn the דף daf for a second,
which is why it's gonna be a super short דף daf today.
Okay, you have this huge תוספות Tosafos there. It is not one
of these תוספות Tosafos names that's trying to figure out how to
deal with a lot of contradictory סוגיות. sugyos. It's basically just trying
to figure out what פשט pshat in this one line is that
we just read. רש"י Rashi gives a פשט pshat and then this
תוספות Tosafos goes back and forth whether he agrees with רש"י Rashi
or doesn't agree with רש"י. Rashi. What is this third דרשה drasha
about? So this third דרשה, drasha, the way רש"י Rashi explains it,
is to tell you: how do you know that all of the
קרבנות korbanos that you do on the outer מזבח mizbeach you spill
the blood at the base? Because the only קרבנות korbanos that it
says spill the blood at the base are the חטאות. chata'os. Yeah
but you didn't realize that. Go back and look. When all the
other קרבנות, korbanos, it does not say spill the blood at the
base. Now part of the reason might be how do you put
what do you do with the blood of the other חטאות, chata'os,
of the other קרבנות? korbanos? How do you apply them on the
מזבח, mizbeach, do you know?
But you have
שתים שהן ארבע shtayim she-hen arba and how do you apply them?
זריקה. zrikah. You throw them. So with the חטאת chatas you use
your finger and you do the corners, there's a lot of blood
left. Here if you're doing this, probably all of it is going
to go out and hit, there's nothing left. So maybe it's not
the פסוקים pesukim are assuming you don't have. have leftover. But in
case you have leftover, they don't tell you what to do with
the blood. Okay, so רש״י Rashi is saying that this point of
מזבח העולה mizbach haolah is telling you, the מזבח העולה, mizbach haolah,
the יסוד yesod is like relevant for everything that's on the מזבח
העולה. mizbach haolah. Any קרבן korban that's on this outer thing, יסוד
מזבח העולה, yesod mizbach haolah, the יסוד yesod matters in the sense
that spill the שירים shirayim on the יסוד yesod if there are
שירים. shirayim. So that's to tell you the principle of spill the
שירים. shirayim.
Wait, but it says תן יסוד למזבח העולה, tein yesod l'mizbach haolah,
it means put it on the יסוד. yesod.
No, no, no, he means for the מזבח העולה, mizbach haolah, the
יסוד yesod always has blood that's going to be put on it
or is the יסוד yesod is always like a relevant thing. It
doesn't say תן דמים ליסוד. tein damim l'yesod. Okay, well that's why
you have a huge תוספות Tosfos here because it's a very vague
phrase. So תוספות, Tosfos, the other really alternative פשט, p'shat, I mean
he has like a couple of variations on a theme, but the
other alternative פשט p'shat that תוספות Tosfos has it means is because
there is where was no יסוד yesod at this corner. The sort
of way it went was sort of like like it went like
this and it went like here. I mean, I guess maybe I'll
draw the יסוד yesod with a different color.
The יסוד yesod sort of went like this. No base.
Okay, so there was no יסוד yesod at this corner. So the
question is, how do you know where the blood is thrown? There's
another principle. When you're throwing the blood of an עולה olah or
whatever, it has to be where there's a base, a protruding base.
Obviously everything had a base, it wasn't floating in mid-air. There was
a protruding base below the corners. So you throw the blood here
and here, you don't throw the blood here. If you threw it
at diagonal corner, you don't throw it here and here because over
here there's no base. So תוספות Tosfos says the דרשה drasha of
תן יסוד למזבח העולה tein yesod l'mizbach haolah means wherever you're going
to put the blood on the מזבח העולה, mizbach haolah, other than
the corner of the חטאת, chatat, which is up here, but when
you're going to put it, throw it on the wall, it has
to be where there's a base below it. Both of those הלכות
halachot are true. The question is just where are we learning it
from.
So תוספות Tosfos would still agree that for every קרבן korban you're
still pouring.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. The question is just where do we learn it
from this פסוק. pasuk.
Anyway, according to רש״י, Rashi, you're still pouring it all on one
corner on the west one?
On the western?
That's a debate as I said, but that's not clear. That's as
I said a debate.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, so that's
third the third דרשה drasha is the one that's less clear what
we're saying.
אל יסוד מזבח העולה, al yesod mizbach haolah, תן יסוד למזבח שלה,
tein yesod l'mizbach shelah, which for רש״י Rashi means pour all the
blood on the outer altar on the base. All the remainder blood.
או אינה אלא מזבחה של עולה יהא לו יסוד, o eina ela
mizivcha shel olah yehei lo yesod,
maybe what it's actually saying is the way רש״י Rashi reads this
הוה אמינא havah amina is exactly what תוספות Tosfos says that that
that we are learning. רש״י Rashi says maybe this פסוק pasuk is
coming to tell you that when you put, I don't get how
he's reading it in these words, when you put the initial blood
of an עולה, olah, it has to be opposite the base, meaning
maybe this third דרשה drasha is not telling you spill the remainder
on the base, but put the initial blood where there's a base
below. Maybe that's what it's telling me. Okay, which again is the
correct הלכה, halacha, okay, it's just that is that what it's telling
me or not. אמר רבי ישמעאל amar Rabbi Yishmael קל וחומר. kal
v'chomer. No, you don't need the פסוק pasuk to tell you that
you throw the blood of the עולה olah where there's a base
below because I can learn it from a קל וחומר. kal v'chomer.
What's the קל וחומר? kal v'chomer? מה שירים שאין מכפרים טעונים יסוד,
mah shirayim she'ein mechapperim te'unim yesod,
when the remnant which don't create כפרה kaparah have to be poured
out on the base, תחילת עולה, tchilat olah, the blood of the
the initial placing, the initial throwing of the blood, שמכפרת shemechapperes which
achieves atonement, אינו דין שטעון יסוד, eino din shete'un yesod, of course
it needs a base, so you don't need to learn it from
this פסוק pasuk מזבח העולה. mizbach haolah. Again, the way רש״י Rashi
is reading it in is, how do we know the הלכה halacha
that the initial throwing of blood is at these corners where there's
a base below? Not from the פסוק pasuk of מזבח העולה, mizbach
haolah, we know it from a קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. If the
spilling of the blood is required, which by a חטאת chatat or
whatever it might be, has to be done on a base, and
that's not atoning, right? Certainly the initial blood has to have a
base below. Okay, so therefore the idea that the initial blood has
to have a base below, I can learn from a קל וחומר.
kal v'chomer. The extra פסוק pasuk is telling me that even by
an עולה, olah, if there's remainder blood, also pour that out at
the base. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says essentially the same thing, sounds
like almost word for word. The גמרא Gemara is going to try
to figure out how it's different. אמר רבי עקיבא, amar Rabbi Akiva,
מה שירים שאין מכפרים, mah shirayim she'ein mechapperim, the remnant isn't מכפר
mechapper ואין באים לכפר, v'ein ba'im l'chapper, it's not even coming for
כפרה, kaparah, טעונים יסוד, te'unim yesod, and that needs to be spilled
out at the base, like say by a חטאת, chatat, תחילת עולה
שמכפרת ובאה לכפר, tchilat olah shemechapperes uva'ah l'chapper, אינו דין שטעון יסוד,
eino din shete'un yesod, so certainly the initial blood needs a base.
So therefore רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael are
saying, look, we know that the initial blood of an עולה olah
has a base underneath it from a קל וחומר kal v'chomer from
the fact that שירים shirayim needs a base. So what's this third
מזבח העולה mizbach haolah teaching me? Again, the way רש״י Rashi reads
it is it's telling me that if you have שירים shirayim of
an עולה, olah, spill those out on the base as well. That's
the ברייתא *Braita*. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to unpack it.
Or a שלמים *Shelamim* too, right? Anything, or a שלמים *Shelamim*, any
of it.
Okay, אם כן מה תלמוד לומר יסוד Yesod. מזבח Mizbeach. עולה Olah
*Im kein ma talmud lomar Yesod Mizbe'ach Olah*? תן יסוד למזבח של
עולה ten yesod lamizbeach shel olah *Tain yesod l'mizbe'ach shel olah*. Again,
very vague. Okay, which explains why there's a lot of discussion. אמר
מר *Amar mar*: אל יסוד מזבח העולה El Yesod Mizbeach Ha-Olah. *al
yesod mizbe'ach ha-olah*, ולא יסוד Yesod, מזבח Mizbeach הפנימי *velo yesod mizbe'ach
ha-penimi*. Okay, so the first דרשה drasha *drasha* is pour it on
the outer altar, not the inner one. So the base, by the
inner חטאות *chata'ot*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: המיבעי ליה לגופיה
*Ha miba'ei lei legufei*. One minute. Maybe, how do you know when
it says pour the blood of the inner חטאות *chata'os* on the
outer altar, the base of the outer altar, it's saying and not
the base of the inner altar? A general principle as we said
in the שיעור *shiur* a little while ago and we've been saying
is you need things to be repeated to say it's מעכב me’akev.
*me'akeiv*. So maybe it's only saying it: pour it on the outer
one, if you want you can also do it on the inner
one, but you know it's not מעכב me’akev, *me'akeiv* because שירים sheyariyim
*shirayim* is not מעכב me’akev. *me'akeiv*, at least according to our משנה
mishna *mishna*, but anyway. But maybe when it says pour it on
the outer one it doesn't mean only the outer one, it means
also you could also do it on the outer one, either the
inner or the outer. How do you know it means only the
outer? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no: מאשר פתח אהל מועד
נפקא *me'asher petach ohel mo'ed nafka*. It could have just said spill
it על יסוד Yesod המזבח אשר פתח אהל מועד *al yesod hamizbe'ach
asher petach ohel mo'ed* because it already says אשר פתח אהל מועד
*asher petach ohel mo'ed*. Why does it have the extra word עולה
Olah *Olah*? The extra word עולה Olah *Olah* is telling you only
that מזבח Mizbeach *mizbe'ach* is where it gets spilled, not the inner
one. אל יסוד מזבח העולה El Yesod Mizbeach Ha-Olah *Al yesod mizbe'ach
ha-olah*, so the extra עולה Olah *Olah* tells you only the outer
one. Then the fact that it says העולה *ha-olah* a second time
tells you oh, by the way, the reason it's only the outer
one is because the inner one doesn't even have a יסוד yesod.
*yesod*. Okay, and then the third דרשה *drasha* is what we just
said, which is תן יסוד yesod למזבח העולה *Tain yesod l'mizbe'ach ha-olah*
which for רש"י Rashi *Rashi* means all blood that has שירים sheyariyim
*shirayim* always gets spilled at that base. תן יסוד yesod, למזבח של
עולה *Tain yesod l'mizbe'ach shel olah*—דאיסלקא דעתך כדיכתיב *de'isalka daitchach k'dechasiv*, so
הני למה לי קרא *hani lamma li kra* לשירים *le-shirayim*? שירים sheyariyim
דבראי לבראי הוו *Shirayim de-barai le-barai havu*. Maybe, אה *ah*, רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* says wait, maybe says the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* the third
application—these two are the inner חטאות *chata'ot*. So these two it says
מזבח העולה Mizbeach Ha-Olah *mizbe'ach ha-olah*, it's an inner חטאת Chatas *chatas*
but spill the blood on the outer מזבח Mizbeach. *mizbe'ach*. It's an
inner חטאת chatas *chatas*, don't spill it at the base of the
inner מזבח Mizbeach. *mizbe'ach* because the inner מזבח Mizbeach *mizbe'ach* doesn't have
a base. Now you get to the שעיר נשיא *Se'ir Nasi*. The
שעיר נשיא *Se'ir Nasi* is an outer חטאת chatas *chatas*. So maybe
the reason it says מזבח העולה Mizbeach Ha-Olah *mizbe'ach ha-olah* is to
tell you not only do the inner חטאות *chata'ot* get their blood
spilled on the outer base, the outer חטאת chatas *chatas* also get
its blood spilled on the outer base. Okay, which is true. So
maybe it's not some new fancy דרשה *drasha*, maybe it's just a
simple point. Not only the inner one on the outer base, the
outer. Now of course you could say it's a קל וחומר Kal
Vachomer. *kal vachomer*. If the inner one on the outer base, certainly
the outer one is on the outer base. That's the bit of
קל וחומר Kal Vachomer *kal vachomer*—כאילו מנה הני קל וחומר Kal Vachomer
*k'ilu m'na hanei kal vachomer*. But you could have said no, maybe
it's like well maybe you always flip it. Flip the switch. Maybe
it's a chiasmic structure. דאיסלקא דעתך כדיכתיב *De'isalka
daitach k'dechasiv*—if all it's telling you is an outer חטאת *chatas*, the
blood is spilled on the outer base,
הני למה לי קרא *hani lamma li kra* for שירים sheyariyim *shirayim*?
שירים sheyariyim. דבראי לבראי הוו *Shirayim de-barai le-barai havu*.
You're doing the whole קרבן Korban *korban* on the outside, of course
you're going to spill the blood on the outer base. וכי תימא
דאפיך מיפך *Vechi teima de-afich meifich*—no, maybe I would have had a
הוה אמינא *hava amina*, you know, switch it. דבראי לגואי *Debara ligavai*—the
outer חטאת *chatas* you spill the blood on the inner, ודגואי לבראי
*ude-gavai le-bara*—the inner חטאת *chatas* you spill the blood on the outer.
Okay, so maybe I need the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* to just tell
you the פשט *pshat*—spill the blood on the outer. No, you don't
need it for that. Why? Because the second דרשה *drasha* already told
us there is no base on the inner, so it's not even
a possibility. הא אין לה יסוד yesod. לפנימי עצמו *Ha ain lah
yesod le-penimi atzmo*. Okay, so therefore clearly once I've said there's no
base here, by the time I get here I don't have to
say spill it on the outer base, of course the outer חטאת
*chatas* spilled on the outer base, there is no inner base to
spill it on. Okay, so the extra פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* is telling
me this idea of תן יסוד yesod למזבח של עולה *Tain yesod
l'mizbe'ach shel olah*, which for רש"י *Rashi* basically just means all שירים
sheyariyim, *shirayim* get spilled on the outer base. We're going to read
it like רש"י *Rashi*. So now let's just go through that. Okay,
we'll get a little ahead.
Okay, או אינו אלא *o eino ela*—so now we're quoting the ברייתא
*braita* again. או אינו אלא מזבח Mizbeach, של עולה יהיה ליסוד *O
eino ela mizbe'ach shel olah yiheye le-yesod*. So now...
you
see that's like so confusing, המזבח *hamizbe'ach* or זבח *zevach*?
מזבח Mizbeach *Mizbe'ach*, I think it means מזבח Mizbeach, *mizbe'ach* is the
way רש"י *Rashi* reads it. Maybe it means, so now the ברייתא
*braita* continues, again reading the ברייתא *braita* through the way רש"י *Rashi*
reads it. Maybe it just means that the initial placing of blood
of an עולה *Olah* is opposite a base, maybe that's the point
of this last דרשה *drasha* of מזבח העולה Mizbeach Ha-Olah *mizbe'ach ha-olah*?
So no, מי כתיב על יסוד העולה Yesod Ha-Olah, *mi kesiv al
yesod ha-olah*? על יסוד מזבח העולה mizbeach ha'olah. כתיב *Al yesod mizbe'ach
ha-olah kesiv*. That's what the ברייתא *braita* says. It doesn't say... no,
actually the ברייתא *braita* says a קל וחומר Kal Vachomer. *kal vachomer*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying one minute,
before you get to the קל וחומר Kal Vachomer, *kal vachomer* to
prove that you already know that the blood goes here, I'll tell
you how you know that we're talking about the blood going there,
that we're not talking about the blood going there. If we were
talking about the blood going there, we would have said אל יסוד
העולה. El Yesod Ha-Olah. What would I have said? אל יסוד העולה.
El Yesod Ha-Olah, It wouldn't just have said אל יסוד מזבח העולה.
El Yesod Mizbeach Ha-Olah Now why would one of that meant that?
Because רש״י Rashi says, if it's talking about the קרבן Korban that
the עולה blood goes at these corners, then just say אל יסוד
העולה, El Yesod Ha-Olah, like the עולה is opposite the יסוד. אל,
El,
meaning if that were to tell you about where initially the blood
of the קרבן Korban, goes. מזבח Mizbeach. העולה is basically really telling
you a principle about the actual מזבח. Mizbeach. The מזבח Mizbeach and
its base always has blood spilled on it. It's not telling you
what you do with a particular קרבן, Korban it's telling you the
מזבח always has the blood spilled at its base. Okay, again, if
this seems a little vague and not persuasive, go read this תוספות,
Tosafot, you'll see if you're any half happier. Okay, anyway, I just
tell you I read the תוספות. Tosafot. If I thought there was
a different read that was much more persuasive, I would have given
it to you. So anyway, okay, so the גמרא Gemara says no,
אל יסוד מזבח העולה כתיב. El Yesod Mizbeach Ha-Olah Kesiv. So so
that's how you know, meaning you don't need the קל וחומר. Kal
Vachomer. Clearly we're not talking about the initial application of blood, because
if we were talking about the initial application of blood, it would
just have said אל יסוד העולה, El Yesod Ha-Olah, which would have
emphasized the עולה קרבן Korban that you're bringing. No, אי הוי כתיב
אל יסוד העולה, Ei Hava Kesiv El Yesod Ha-Olah, had it said
that, הוה אמינא בזקיפה של יסוד, Hava Amina Bazkifa Shel Yesod, that
maybe what it's because if you think about it, right, the base
looks like this, now we get to show my ability to draw
in 3D.
Okay,
the magnified view.
Magnified, this is the base, okay, so it goes up one טפח,
Tefach, and then the next stage it goes like this or whatever,
actually then the next stage it goes like that.
So this is the base. It's one טפח. Tefach. So when so
it says like this, had it said יסוד העולה, which would have
told me put the blood, oh and here,
this corner doesn't have the base, whatever, however it works. Okay, anyway,
so if it had said that, I just would have said right,
meaning we're trying to say you know by a קל וחומר Kal
Vachomer it goes on these two corners, and you don't need אל
יסוד מזבח העולה to tell you. אל יסוד מזבח העולה is telling
you pour the שיריים. Shirayim. But the גמרא says wait, I know
it's not talking about the initial application of blood because if so
it just would have said אל יסוד העולה, El Yesod Ha-Olah it
would have emphasized the קרבן Korban עולה and not it wouldn't have
used the word מזבח. So the גמרא says no, here's why it's
using the word מזבח. If it would have said the word אל
יסוד העולה to tell you the initial blood goes on the קרבנות,
Korbanot, I would have said that you know which corners they go
on? They go on the actual corner of the יסוד, and they
go on the זקיפה, Zkifa, like the vertical, okay, the upright. Okay,
the fact that it says מזבח somehow tells you it can go
on the יסוד that is like a מזבח, and like a מזבח
somehow means the top of it. I don't know why that's like
a מזבח, because I guess you burn stuff at the top of
a מזבח. I mean, you also throw the blood at the rise
of the מזבח.
It's also so much easier to like, you know, spill it just
like on,
instead of get bent down. Down low, right. So anyway, so somehow
it says this is why I needed the קל וחומר Kal Vachomer?
of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Ishmael. Because even
though the word מזבח is coming to maybe de-emphasize the קרבן and
speak fundamentally that this is used as a base for all קרבנות,
Korbanot, I still could have said it's coming to tell you about
the initial application of blood and telling you put the initial application
of blood here, which is the הלכה, Halacha, I mean the הלכה
Halacha isn't you put it there, you actually the הלכה Halacha is
you put it there. But anyway, okay, so because I would have
said that that's what the combination of the word מזבח העולה is
coming to say, and not the idea that all the spilling of
blood has to be on the base. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael say, ah, but I already know that
the normal initial application of blood is opposite the base based on
a קל וחומר. kal vachomer So that's not what the פסוק pasuk
is telling, so the פסוק is rather teaching about the spill that
all the blood gets spilled, all the קרבנות, Korbanot, if there's extra
blood, gets spilled on the base. Okay, so let's just read that.
אי הוי כתיב אל יסוד העולה הוה אמינא בזקיפה
של יסוד. Ei Hava Kesiv El Yesod Ha-Olah Hava Amina Bazkifa Shel
Yesod. השתא דכתיב אל יסוד מזבח העולה אגגו דיסוד. Hashta Dechesiv El
Yesod Mizbeach Ha-Olah Agago De-Yesod. I would have said that means on
the roof of the base. Anyway, so that's if it had said
מזבח העולה without a קל וחומר, I might have said it applies
to the initial application of blood, that it has to be opposite
the base and not the idea that all שיריים Shirayim of all
קרבנות Korbanot go to the base. So how do you know? So
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael says fine, but that I don't need because
I know that from a קל וחומר. אמר רבי ישמעאל אגגו דיסוד
למה לי קרא קל וחומר, Amar Rabbi Ishmael Agago De-Yesod Lama Li
Kra Kal Vachomer, I could learn from a קל וחומר that you
need initial blood to be out either on the top of the
of the base or opposite the base. What's the
קל וחומר? ומה שירי חטאת שאינה מכפרת טעונה גג יסוד, Umah Shirei
Chatas She-eina Mechaperet Te'unah Gago Shel Yesod, the same way the remnant
of a חטאת gets spilled
there. תחילה תחילת עולה שמכפרת techila techilas olah she’mechaperes the initial blood
that achieves atonement, אינו דין שטעונה גג יסוד eino din she’te’una gag
yesod how much more so would it be put? Now the funny
thing is that but it's not at the end of the day
put on the גג gag of the יסוד. At the end of
the day it's put over here, you know, which is opposite the
גג gag of the יסוד but not the גג gag of the
יסוד, which again pushes תוספות Tosafot to suggest a different type of
a read of this גמרא. Anyway, but by a קל וחומר I
know the initial blood is opposite of a base.
So this דרשה is teaching me a different הלכה. halacha. Not the
initial blood, but the remnant blood. And now רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says something that sounds almost the exact same.
Excuse me.
אמר רבי עקיבא: Amar Rabbi Akiva: ומה שירי חטאת שאין מכפרים ואין
באין לכפר טעונה גג יסוד תחילת עולה
שמכפרת ובאה לכפר אינו דין שטעונה גג יסוד?
U’ma sheyarei chatas she’ein mechaperim ve’ein ba’in lechaper te’una gag yesod techilas
olah she’mechaperes u’va lechaper eino din she’te’una gag yesod? אם כן מה
תלמוד לומר יסוד המזבח אם לא עניינו לתחילת דם תנהו עניינו לשירי
דם יסוד המזבח עולה תן יסוד למזבח של עולה, Im kein mah
talmud lomar yesod hamizbeach im lo inyano letchilas dam tenahu inyano lishyeirei
dam yesod hamizbeach olah ten yesod lamizbeach shel olah, which again very
vague conclusion, but for רשי it means all of שירים of all
of the outer קרבנות, korbanot, if there is any שירים gets poured
at the base.
מאי בינייהו? Mai beinaihu? What's the difference, we'll read one more line,
between רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי ישמעאל? Rabbi Yishmael? They both
seem to be saying that, you know, they say the same thing.
The spilling of normal שירים isn't מכפר mechaper and it still needs
a יסוד. So רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael said it's not מכפר mechaper
and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said it's not מכפר mechaper and it's
not באין לכפר. ba’in lechaper. What's the difference? They're both making the
same point. So אמר רב אדא בר אהבה: Amar Rav Ada bar
Ahava: שירים מעכבין איכא בינייהו. sheyariyim me’akvin ika beinaihu. Ah, here's the
difference. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says it's not מכפר, mechaper, he doesn't
say it's not מעכב. me’akev. Okay, so if you're talking about the
blood, this is what we mentioned before, our משנה assumes that even
the שפיכת שירים shefichas sheyariyim of the inner חטאת is not מעכב,
me’akev, but we did say there is a position that the שפיכת
שירים shefichas sheyariyim of an inner חטאת is מעכב. So the גמרא
is going to say maybe that's the position of רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi
Yishmael. He said the שפיכת שירים shefichas sheyariyim needs a יסוד even
though it's not מכפר. mechaper. It might not be מכפר, mechaper, okay,
its purpose isn't atonement, but doing it prevents atonement. Okay, I mean
not doing it prevents atonement.
Not doing
it prevents atonement, right, it's still מעכב. איכא בינייהו: Ika beinaihu: מר
סבר מעכבין mar savar me’akvin ומר סבר—רבי עקיבא that goes further and
says it's not מכפר mechaper and it's not באין לכפר, ba’in lechaper,
somehow by emphasizing it's not even coming for that purpose, somehow means
like you don't even really need it. Again, I don't know how
you exactly read that in רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva words, but okay.
מר סבר לא מעכבין. mar savar lo me’akvin. It's not מעכב, okay.
So we'll pick up with that tomorrow. The גמרא's going to suggest
another way of explaining the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and
רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, but at least we've moved beyond this basic
thing about תן יסוד למזבח של עולה and what exactly it means.
At the end of the day, רשי and תוספות Tosafot all agree
on the הלכה. halacha. The initial application of blood are at the
corners that do have a base below it and all remnants of
all קרבנות—it korbanot is worth noting that the תורה Torah never mentioned
spilling the שירים by anything other than the חטאת because by most
things maybe there wouldn't even be שירים. But if there were שירים,
it does get poured at the base, okay, and again we're learning
one or the other of these things from this third פסוק of
מזבח העולה. Alright, so we will continue with this tomorrow.
אם ירצה השם אם ירצה השם.
im yirtzeh Hashem im
yirtzeh Hashem.